this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
see radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society IEEE software Magazine
online at computer.org software
for software engineering radio this is
Robert blumen today I have with me
stanislav pazovsky Stan is a graduate of
the University of Warsaw is a developer
at XTX markets in London and formerly
was a software engineer at Google he is
a committer to the jsonate open source
project and that is what we will be
talking about today Stan welcome to
software engineering radio hello
I'm very interested to talk about
jsonnet with you Jason is closely
related to Json I'm guessing most of our
listeners be exposed to that but could
you give us a quick summary of Json and
then we'll move on to jsonnet so Jason
is a very simple I would say mostly a
data interchange format just a tiny
subset of JavaScript but actually like
the JavaScript part isn't that important
it's only the historical part yeah it's
just how everyone saves data visitors so
yeah njsonet is much much more Json is a
programming language it's a language for
building configuration so you write your
program in jsonnet to generate your Json
but it happens that if you every valid
Json is also a programming Json Network
generates with Json which is quite
convenient hence the name what does
jsonnet add that is not there in the
original Json
so it adds the natural programming
language features that you might want in
your configuration file so starting with
variables then functions for templating
there is a form of object orientation
which is somewhat non-standard I believe
we'll talk about this in a bit more
detail later and I believe to import
other files so you don't have to have
your big thing all together and you can
also like reuse pieces in different
configuration files I'm going to put two
questions together and you can answer
them at the same time or one after the
other but why was Json created and what
do you get from having these additional
features that are not there in Json okay
so the original motivation was to create
an open source solution to something
similar to what was used internally at
Google so you have this need when you
have a lot of microservices or in fact
any sort of situation you have like
hundreds of configuration files of we're
using some logic some parts between them
so we don't have to repeat the same file
name over and over again for example or
to make sure things are consistent
between your configuration files and
Google has an internal language for this
purpose but around the time when
kubernetes became popular they've had an
idea to create an open source language
sort of like that with some lessons
learned so I would say better structured
in some ways though actually quite a bit
different in the implementation and yeah
so in 2014 Json net started as a 20
project at Google
so I often find with Json I have some
very long files and one of the things
you mentioned is you have a lot of files
which are quite similar but only
slightly different or within the same
file I have big chunks of code that are
very much repetitive but they're not
exactly the same and if I could just say
I want this block here that's 90 the
same and I want to just change these
three things there isn't really a
natural way to do that with Json but a
programming language should enable me to
do things like that or I could have a
chunk of code and then I reuse that code
is that some of the motivation for this
project yes exactly that so you sort of
have this cycle when like you introduce
some configuration to your program at
first you start with configuration
inside your program just like as part of
your Source when you start extracting it
you first have like a simple
configuration file with just a few
parameters but then as it grows it turns
out that you need variables you need to
reuse parts of this and then like you
want to have some templates because
things are not always exactly the same
then you want to add impulse to share
things between files and then you sort
of reinvented the whole programming
language just specifically for the
purpose of your program usually in a
quiet ad-hoc basis of the outcome of
this process usually isn't of very high
quality so what jsonet does is sort of
gives you a generic solution to that
problem it gives you like something that
you can use to have this complex
configuration and manage complex
configuration for your software and
there are two ways to approach that one
is from the offer of a program
perspective which is oh I don't want to
invent my new programming language just
to specify my complex config in a
convenient way so I can just use Json
and suggest that someone can use jsonnet
or one of the comparable Solutions
instead and actually I don't even need
to car which one the user actually
chooses in the end and the second
perspective is sort of from the user's
point of view so let's say I have a lot
of microservices or just a lot of
configuration and organization and I can
have a centralized mechanism to generate
all of this configuration and share some
parts between them just now you said
something I hadn't thought of the way I
would have seen this being used and the
way I'm using it in my job right now is
we have a tool chain that runs a bunch
of jsonnet programs and generates Json
and pushes those out to where the
configuration can be consumed you
mentioned that you could teach your
program to use jsonnet as the
configuration language so the program
instead of reading Json would
incorporate Json it in that situation
would you embed the jsonnet language
into your program and have it process
your config files
you can't do that as sort of a quality
of life feature but what I would
normally recommend is just to consume
Json and then like you don't even need
to impose jsonnet specifically on your
users when the user can make a final
Choice whether to use a sonnet or doll
or whatever they like or like even if
their use case is simple enough just
Json did then they don't need all of
this extra complexity so you can just
not care about this at all just consume
Json or yaml and the users can generate
veg Json that you can consume with based
on it so my understanding is yaml is a
superset of Json does jsonnet
interoperate with yaml equally well
in a way yes because Json generates Json
and Jason is a subset of yaml if you
generate Json with jsonnet this is
automatically also yamo so in this sense
like you can always it's not the Json
that is generated by Json that it's not
idiomatic yaml but this can be
automatically transformed if you really
care but yeah you can just take the Json
that is emitted by jsonnet and have it
interpreted as yaml and it will work
we've been using my job another Library
that's written in Json it's called graph
on it which generates Json input for the
grafana dashboard system one of the
things I found very helpful about this
is grafana has an enormous number of
parameters of which many of them are not
well documented and I don't know what
they all mean the library provides
rational defaults for almost everything
so I can get productive on a programming
task without understanding every single
variable whereas if I was writing it
directly in Json I would have to know
quite a lot more so by abstracting and
defaulting it makes me much more
productive I want to ask are there other
libraries or packages in the ecosystem
similar to that that you're aware of for
other services that use a lot of Json
there are a few I'd say that probably
the most important ones are for
kubernetes a few of them I think the
best one currently is just called
kubernetes and the Json Eclipse
organizational GitHub but for a few out
there but like this is mostly useful in
cases of like actually very complex
config formats but I think you can very
successfully just like use your vanilla
Json net to generate your config like
this is very much like an optional thing
to have a library specific for your
output configuration in the kubernetes
case then there's Jason and the
associated libraries become a competitor
to tools like helm I'm not sure maybe on
some level I don't have a very strong
opinion here I think sometimes where I
used to gather to some extent I'm not
sure could I if I for some reason I
didn't like jsona or just trying to make
a point about something comparable to
this could I do all my programming in my
favorite language whatever that is let's
say python which has data structures and
has all the programming language
features and then at the end export to
Json what would be the pros and cons of
that versus jsonnet yeah I think this is
a very valid approach why would you want
to use Json instead of like whatever you
are currently using so far a few things
so first if your language is something
like C plus plus then there's a lot of
boilerplate just like managing with
extra files things like the way you
express Json is just not very ergonomic
so it's much easier to especially in the
like fairly lightweight configuration
when you use it most less here is my
Json output with just a few things being
changed dynamically in such cases yeah
just jsonnet offers you much better like
day to day developer experience and
second thing is hermeticity and this is
sort of a funny feature because this is
about what we don't do rather than what
we do do it is a guarantee that jsonnet
won't randomly read some files or have
any additional side effects so in
principle you should be able to take
your whole Json net code base run it
five years from now on a completely
different architecture and get bite for
byte the same result and found no hidden
dependencies jsonnet programs cannot
just like all of the files that jsonnet
can access is known statically I've
heard this word before I had to look it
up the word hermetic in dictionary.com a
hermetic seal ensures perfect
waterproofing yeah this is what we are
getting at so vaidya is you can think of
jsonet program as a mathematical
function not only in the implementation
detail sense but there are actually no
side effects no unexpected interaction
with the file system or another Network
or anything like that which in general
purpose language that would be a fatal
flaw but for configuration language you
don't really want all of these things to
be happening so you have the separation
you have well-specified inputs which
produces your well-specified output so
where I think you're going with that is
if you're on a Python program you can
pretty much do anything you want and in
Security in the supply chain we really
want things that cannot do anything they
want because they could do a lot of harm
I wouldn't stress the security aspect
here I would say it's mostly about
making things understandable because
normally config files are not super well
tested and I was like there's really no
need for all of this extra interactions
like usually it means that someone is
taking some weird shortcuts but actually
like you want what determines your
configuration to be very well
understandable and also you might want
to run it in your CI environment or
something like that and then all of the
extra dependencies on the environmental
transient are potential headaches so
this is the primary motivation in terms
of security well I would say that yes
it's safer to run arbitrary Jason and
run arbitrary python for example this is
the programming language and this is the
like arbitrary code execution which may
take arbitrary amounts of time so treat
jsonnet code AS code not as data I want
to move on more now into the language
itself what does a jsonnet program look
like
so the simplest jsons programs look like
just Json but then you can add a few
additional things so the most important
one I'd say is functions and function
calls so you can just Define your own
function which effectively parametrized
part of your Json then reuse it in
multiple places variables are even more
basic than like you are just specifying
one specific thing how do you run a
jsonnet program what happens when you
run it
so normally Json the programs are run in
one of two modes one is just like you
run the jsonnet command and you specify
all of the extra inputs that are
injected as I said before like it cannot
just reach out for things so you need to
pass everything explicitly and then it's
going to evaluate the expression that
your program is and output your Json or
in fact the Versa mode which lets you
output arbitrary strings so for
generating any other config files
so unlike a general purpose programming
language you don't have to say print F
or any type of output command the
purpose of the program is to run to
produce its output which is Json and
that's what it does every single time
correct exactly it doesn't necessarily
have to be Json in the output it can
also be any other data but it is Json by
default so if you just have a program
which consists on a single string the
output will be a Json string but if you
run it with dash s then it will actually
output that string as just a not as Json
without the quotes So this is how it
normally works there is also a library
API so you can also call it directly
from your programs and then yeah you
don't use the command line interface but
it's pretty much in case it has an API
then in what different programming
languages support that API so there are
a few there's a c API which is I would
say most generic and you can use this
bindings from whatever you want for also
C plus plus bindings first a go API
there is an alternative implementation
rust I'm not sure if it has rust API but
I would guess it has various also a
Scala implementation with API for jvm
like a lot of programming languages
these days it incorporates ideas from
all over the programming language map so
we could discuss some of these different
concepts one is that it is largely
declarative
do you delve into that a bit so I'm not
sure what you're you're getting at with
declarative but what I can say is like
it's pure and Order of evaluation
doesn't really matter so you pretty much
think of a program mostly as a function
like a mathematical function and you
think of everything in terms of its
definition so in that sense it's
declarative so like you're not thinking
in terms of hey here is a program which
tells the machine to do this and then
that and then something else we are
saying oh here is a value which consists
of this parts and then it's up to jsonet
interpreter to evaluate them in a
reasonable way where are we going with
that is Json document is a jsonnet
program and if I ran it I would get the
document back maybe I wanted to add a
single variable that would be calculated
by a function and make that be a value
of a field in the document so I can add
that and I run the program and now I get
the document but it's interpolated the
value of the variable the program is
essentially a document and I can
manipulate different parts of the
document through these programming
language constructs but it's really just
a document that's how I saw it is am I
thinking about it the wrong way yeah I
think this is exactly correct so yeah
like I think the best practice is to
have a jsonet file for each output file
that you want to produce and think in
terms of what parts does it need to have
and then have appropriate object fields
or whatever you need inside that file
and then it can import some additional
files for anything you want to have
reused
also incorporates some object-oriented
Concepts can you explain the object
orientation model right so we start with
just like normal Json objects which are
just key value Maps where keys are
strings and values can be any jsonate
values which are Json values and
functions functions are one additional
type that we have on top of what Json
has but we also have a quite unique
concept of objects overriding each other
which is how object orientation Works in
jsonnet and the way to think about it is
an object is a stack of layers each
layer has some fields and when I write a
plus b When A and B are objects then the
new object the resultant object is first
all of the layers from a and then all of
the layers from B on top and then when I
use any self-referential constructs
which are self or super it looks through
the layers to find the appropriate field
to access so if somewhere in my one
field of my object uses self.full what
happens is it will start looking from
the top of a stack of layers for the
field called Foo and super is similar to
how super Works in object-oriented
languages and in the stack of layers
terms it starts looking for your super
dot Foo in the layers below the current
layer from which it is called so it is a
mixing based inheritance model where you
can treat every single object as a
mixing so yeah there are no declaration
in Json it whatsoever everything is just
an expression so this is how you can get
inheritance without any declarations
use the word mix in and I'm aware that
many languages have a concept of mixing
can you explain a bit more what do you
mean by mixing within jsonnet yeah so
mixin is just an object which expects to
be used to override another object so
for example it might add an additional
field I know let's say I have a web
server configuration and I can have a
mixing which adds a https configuration
to my route or something and it can
refer to the fields from the whole
object the
so in order to add https then I might
need to add some additional
keys and values that are not in the base
object or maybe I might have to change
the way something is done in the base
object and it's possible to both add and
change things with a mix in is that
right exactly you can either add new
fields or overwrite existing ones it is
not currently possible to remove files
completely you can override them to null
which usually is good enough
so I like that web server example could
you give another example of how
inheritance was used the true Arab to do
something useful not necessarily
involving a mix in but an example that
shows the object-oriented feature of
jsonnet
so I think all of these examples are
quite similar and these are for the use
of actual fully fledged inheritance and
it is you have different aspects of your
configuration so it can also be I know
your rate limit or some resource limits
depends on what you are trying to
configure obviously and one style of
writing jsonnet is to combine a bunch of
mixings each of this makes sense is
responsible for one aspect of
configuration and then you can just use
the operator plus to combine this into
your final full configuration
and depending on your use case you might
find the same mix in could be used
across different root documents is that
right yes yes and for like some of this
libraries also just like offer mixins
which can be used by by anyone so for
example for configuring kubernetes it
will automatically create the right
Fields Etc
right because many kubernetes objects
although the type is different they
contain a lot of the same elements in
the body so there's definitely
opportunity for some reuse there that's
right that's right and if you have a
strict hierarchical object orientation
it's difficult to reuse
things that are in a derived class
because you can only derive from one
base class or as a mix-in enables you to
take the same derived behavior and apply
it very flexibly yes that's true and
jsonnet offers one more thing on top
which is quite unusual you can create an
Uber mixing out of multiple mixins so
the plus operator is used for
inheritance to jsonnet which is quite an
unusual choice but it actually is
related to how of a semantics because of
inheritance in jsonet has a lot of
similarities with concatenation because
it's just concatenating these layers so
it's an associative operation and you
can build all of the mixins you need
before you add it to the actual thing
you don't need to start with the base
layer and then add it one by one you can
combine them together first
in some of the documentation Json is
described as a functional programming
language what are some of the functional
programming features of Json yes I think
it's more functional than object
oriented especially when use 12. so the
primary functional characteristic is
Purity so you structure your programs by
writing expressions with evaluate to a
single value there is no mutable State
whatsoever
and I would say that the default way of
how to parameterize things is by
introducing functions so you can in fact
wrap any jsonet expression in a function
and parameterize it this way and because
like Json net programs are composed
entirely of Expressions this is actually
very powerful you can take your entire
file wrap it in a function and now you
have a parametrizable module does it
accept functions as arguments to other
functions yes yes functions are regular
values you can pass them around freely
very completely first class objects the
only thing you cannot do with functions
is you cannot print them out or compare
them so but this is this is quite
expected I believe
in the documentation there's a section
about the lazy semantics that you can
modify something while you're creating
it can you explain how that works yes so
jsonnet is a lazy language and that
means that every expression is evaluate
only at the point when it is needed this
is similar to how Haskell works for
example but it's not actually anything
esoteric the main benefit of that is you
don't need to worry at all about order
of how you define things you can have
one object field which refers to another
object field so let's say you start with
a simple Json object with no extra logic
whatsoever and you start parameterizing
it and you decide that one field should
depend on the value of another field you
can just do that and you don't have to
worry about oh but which field is
actually created first as long as there
are no actual Cycles in the definitions
it will all just automatically work for
you and how is that helpful or can you
give an example of what you might do
with that I'd say it's mostly just a
quality of life thing because
technically you could always just
extract things in the right order but
you don't have to think about this at
all you can extract every definition you
have in your code to a variable and you
don't have to worry about oh but
actually this needs some thing which is
defined later and this is especially
important when the data is deeper so you
have objects which has have objects as
its fields which in turn have objects as
Fields so you can have object a which
depends on some fields of object B and
then object B in terms depends on some
other fields of object a but as long as
there are no actual Cycles on the level
of individual primitive values then it's
all fine now given the nature of what
you're trying to do and how constrained
it is I'm gonna guess there's not really
a need for things like exception
handlers at either the program runs or
it doesn't and if it runs you get an
output is that correct yes we have a
primitive form of error handling which
is just you have an error expression
which just throws a fatal ER versus no
error recovery yeah there's really no
need because the idea is Json never
needs to interact with any external
systems so there's no need this is just
all pure computation why would you want
to yeah right so it's not sitting there
retrying to connect to the database
until it succeeds exactly so there is no
need for any advanced error handling and
in general we are trying to keep the
language minimal and very very simple so
if something isn't needed it's it's not
that
now covering the language features I
want to go into the tool chain you
mentioned before that there is a jsonnet
command that you can run it are there
other auxiliary commands like is there a
formatter package manager any other
parts of the ecosystem
yes so the format is a very important
one so it's normally distributed
together with a jsonnet interpreter it's
called dissonant fmt and it has a few
configuration options but it's also a
bit opinionated and there's also linta a
linta which actually was a bit of an
engineering challenge because we have no
types whatsoever and yet we have fairly
complex structures to work with and
field names of objects can be calculated
dynamically but usually aren't and to
deal with all of that a special inter
was created which sort of constructs a
set of equations on sets for each value
in the program and then tries to solve
which values can appear in different
places of the program and mostly it
catches things like using a field which
doesn't exist
can you think of any other types of
errors that the linter could find it can
also find some classes of infinite loops
and things like unknown variable names
are caught by the basic interpreter so
in fact all of the usages of variables
are always statically known we talked a
little bit about there is some ecosystem
of libraries does Json it offer a
package manager so where is the third
part you want it's called jsonnet
bundler first a bunch of packages
available it's not super mature yet but
it works and to the extent that you
actually need libraries I think it's
pretty good
is there a any type of testing framework
or whether
you say yes or no how do people go about
testing jsonnet programs
so the exists uh testing library but
like I would say the number one way to
test jsonnet programs is for technical
golden testing so you would just save
the value of your output of known good
output to a file and then whenever it
changes you would just inspect the div
in the output this is how we test Json
interpreter itself we just have a bunch
of examples of jsonet programs and we
compare the output against the known
good one but in some cases it's easier
to have something more akin to unit
tests versus a built-in support for
assertions in jsonnet there are also a
few third-party libraries
and moving on what language is it
implemented in how many implementations
are there and what languages are are
they written in
so the four implementations which I
would call production quality the
original one written in C plus plus
which isn't very efficient then there is
a go implementation which is the closest
one to the official one currently this
is the one that I spent most of of my
time on versus also an implementation in
Scala created by data bricks I haven't
used it but it's known to be quite fast
there is also a new implementation in
Rust called Jr sonat and if you are
wondering why there are so many it's
because jsonnet is a language with first
a very simple language then it has a
well-defined specification there are
actually formal operational semantics
for the language on the website so you
should be able to know exactly what
every construct does so it's actually
like I think it's possible for a decent
engineer to write a acceptable
implementation of jsonnet within months
in my use of it I've been generating
files that are a few thousand lines of
Json and I'm not sure which
implementation I'm using it's whatever I
got on the Mac or the Brew it runs quick
enough that I don't notice it to where I
wouldn't care if it was any faster has
there been any benchmarking or maybe you
could just speak from experience of how
long does it take to run for different
size of either input code base or
outputs
it's hard to say generally other than
like it is still pretty slow even the
fast implementations so performance was
never like a major goal because just for
generating configuration so as you said
in many cases it's not noticeable either
way and I'm not sure about Homebrew but
it might be using actually the original
slowest implementation of them all but
once your output is big enough once you
have for example a thousand jsonet files
then like it can become a bit annoying
so actually the motivation for creating
the skull implementation which was
chronologically the second one it came
before the the go one was just to make
it faster
these different implementations are they
all at the same stage of maturity or are
you still seeing much traffic in terms
of issue reports on any of them
so I have most familiarity with C plus
plants and go one which have uh sort of
official ones and by official I mostly
mean that they are maintained by Dave
who is the original author of The
Language and like we definitely still
see issues they are about smaller and
smaller things like additions to the
standard library or actually creating
these external tools so Jason lintel was
2019 early 2020 Edition and we still see
a steady stream of PRS but the language
itself doesn't change very much this is
mostly about additional tooling
extension of a standout Library Etc
standard library now I realize I wanted
to ask about that so I'm glad you
mentioned that what are some of the
offerings of the standard Library
these are mostly very obvious things
that you would expect in the language so
mean and Max functions some basic string
manipulation you know splitting strings
by a DOT if you need to converting ASCII
to uppercase passing Focus values you
can pause Json to pass yaml with also
some functions which lets you
automatically produce various formats so
you can produce an ini file or a python
object or in fact a Json but within your
program so in some cases some weird
formats require some Json embedded as a
string so yes you can do that
ugly as it is or XML or Tomo I think
these are the ones that we currently
include yeah some array functions like
basically what you'd naturally expect
but without anything that relates to
external interactions because that's not
allowed in Json net so like no files no
network you haven't mentioned mentioned
some of the functional programming
Primitives are in standard Library like
map and fold right right so this have a
usual definitions so you can write
json's programs in the standard like
functional way with all of the usual
goodies it's the standard Library
implemented in is any of it implemented
in jsonnet or is it all implemented in
the language of the implementation
so historically almost all of the
standard library was implemented in
jsonnet this turned out to be quite slow
so the current approach is every new
addition to the standard Library needs
to have a jsonnet implementation to
guarantee that there is some reasonably
simple definition and it can run on
every platform etc etc but
implementations also provide built-in
versions of these functions and we test
their output matches the reference Json
net implementation but this is only a
performance optimization because jsonnet
as a language is fairly slow so by
implementing some built-in functions in
let's say go we can get often like order
of magnitude improvements
is there an extension point if
programmer wanted to add a function in C
or go to their own Library
yes for exists a native function API you
need to use jsonnet as a library to have
that available it's not very encouraged
because it effectively creates a tiny
dialect but whenever let's say I've used
some complex logic from your project
then you can call that from jsonnet the
Native functions are still supposed to
be pure so things like adding i o
operations adding file operations
through native functions is very
discouraged technically some people do
that with it works we've covered pretty
much what I wanted to about the language
itself if listeners would like to get
started where can they go
so to start using the language the best
place is json.org you can find pretty
much everything I said only much more
clear and we have a bit of an
interactive playground so you can see
how exactly it works on some examples
you can play with them change something
see how it affects the output first
tutorial and a very detailed language
reference and for any potential
contributors I recommend just going to
the GitHub Page open an issue open API
we try to respond in a reasonable time
frame and I think jsonnet is a quite
nice place to start contributing to open
source just because it's quite
self-contained and quite well defined so
it's just quite easy to get started and
if listeners would like to find you
anywhere on the internet where would you
direct them
so if you want to ask me a question
about jsonnet the quickest way is
through slack so there is a slack
channel on kubernetes slack called
jsonnet hash jsonnet this is probably if
you mention me that's probably the
quickest way to get hold of me otherwise
yeah 4json net things open initial on
GitHub or you can always message me on
LinkedIn for other matters
is there anything else you'd like
listeners to know about jsonnet before
we wrap up I think we're good I think
we're good here okay well Stan thank you
very much for speaking to software
engineering radio it's been great thank
you very much
for software engineering radio this has
been Robert blumen thank you for
listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]
thank you